<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Advice to young persons, relating both to faith &amp; practice contain'd in some plain directions how to demean themselves : together with some few motives to the observation of what is here recommended.</title>
            <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1698</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 51 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A93053</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3034A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R42460</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">36281992</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 36281992</idno>
            <idno type="VID">150285</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A93053)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 150285)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2240:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Advice to young persons, relating both to faith &amp; practice contain'd in some plain directions how to demean themselves : together with some few motives to the observation of what is here recommended.</title>
                  <author>Shaw, Samuel, 1635-1696.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 44 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Brabazon Aylmer ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1698]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Samuel Shaw by Wing (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Errata: p. 44.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: tightly bound.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library (London, England)</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Christian life.</term>
               <term>Devotional literature.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>Leah Yurasek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:150285:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p> ADVICE TO Young Perſons, Relating both to <hi>Faith</hi> &amp; <hi>Practice:</hi> Contain'd in ſome Plain Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections how to Demean themſelves.</p>
            <p>Together with ſome few Motives to the Obſervation of what is here recommended.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Wherewithal ſhall a Young Man cleanſe his way? by taking heed thereto according to thy Word,</hi> Pſal. 119. 9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Brabazon Aylmer,</hi> at the <hi>Three Pidgeons</hi> againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil.</hi> Price 2d.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:150285:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:150285:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To his much Honour'd Patron: The Author.</head>
            <p>THo' it is our great Calamity to live in a moſt corrupt Age, Yet by the Influence of the All-wiſe, and All powerful God, (who can derive good out of Evil) you are ſo Prudent, as to make an Advantage of it: and to raiſe the value of your Vertue, and to add to the Luſtre and Worth of your Reputation and Family, by being untainted in the midſt of moſt dangerous Temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>SIR,</hi> I might tell the World, that the following Lines were drawn as a faint Copy from the fair Original which you give, and that the enſuing Precepts are taken from your Pattern: But leſt I ſhould call up the Blood into your Cheeks by offering Violence to your ſingular Modeſty, or throw my ſelf under the Suſpicion of Flattery, I will convert my juſt Praiſes of you, into earneſt Prayers for you, that that good God who hath hitherto pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerv'd
<pb facs="tcp:150285:3" rendition="simple:additions"/> you, would ſtill preſerve you, that you may go on by an <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nſpotted Life ſtill to glorify him; and by your moſt agreeable Temper, to win over others to Piety and Vertue: and to anſwer the Care and Kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of that Learned and Worthy Perſon, by whom your tender Mind was inform'd, and your early Manners cultivated; from whom (in your Minority) I receiv'd the largeſt ſhare of what I have; and ſo stand perpetually oblig'd to return the moſt grateful Acknowledgment. And laſtly, That you may grow in Grace, and in the knowledge of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>til you come to the meaſure of the ſtature of the fullneſs of Chriſt. This is the earneſt Prayer of, Sir,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your moſt Obliged, Moſt devoted, and Moſt Humble Servant.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:150285:3"/>
            <head>ADVICE TO Young Perſons.</head>
            <p>FOraſmuch as 'tis generally ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledg'd, that to perſwade Young Perſons to be Dutiful and Good, would prove an Effectual Means to recover Souls out of the hands of Satan, to reform the World, and to retrieve Religion and Vertue: therefore this ſmall Treatiſe is ſent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broad on purpoſe to exhort, and (if it be poſſible for it) to perſwade thoſe, who in their younger days are more eſpecially beſet with Temptations, and more eaſily invited into a compliance with them; that they ſhould by God's Grace preſerve their ſtanding: Or if fal'n, that they ſhould ſpeedily reſcue
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:150285:4"/> themſelves out of their Slavery, and henceforward fear the Lord always, and keep his Commandments. And may that ſame Good God, who puts into our hearts good Deſires, by his continual help, make us to bring them to good Effect, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, Let me perſwade young Perſons to lay ſuch a ſteady and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhaken Foundation of Faith, that the Gates of Hell may never prevail againſt it. For them who deſign to anſwer the main End of Chriſtianity, this Advice is always ſeaſonable. But never was this Advice more ſeaſonable than it is in our preſent Age, <hi>An Age,</hi> wherein almoſt every particular Perſon is ready to broach ſome particular Opinion; Inſomuch that the old Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marks of Faith are removed, and the main Principles of the Goſpel of Grace and Salvation by Chriſt, doubted of, diſputed, and denied.</p>
            <p>O let it be your great concern then,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt.</hi> To believe in God the Father, who hath made you, and all the World. <hi>Secondly,</hi> in God the Son, who hath redeemed you, and all man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind.
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:150285:4"/> 
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> in God the Holy Ghoſt, who ſanctifieth you, and all the Elect People of God.</p>
            <p>Firſt then, let it be your Concern to believe in God the Father, who by the Son, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. 2. and by the Effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 2. Made the whole World, Heaven and Earth, and all created Beings which are contained therein. And upon this Belief let it be your Buſineſs to give God the Father that Reverence that is due unto him, as our Wonderful Creator. This is that great Lord <hi>who made Heaven and Earth, and the Sea, and all that in them is,</hi> Acts. 4. 24. <hi>This is our Father which is in Heaven,</hi> Mat. 6. 9. <hi>In his Hand are all the Corners of the Earth, and the ſtrength of the Hills is his alſo, the Sea is his and he made it, and his hands prepar'd the dry Land:</hi> And therefore, <hi>O come let us Worſhip, and fall down, and kneel before him!</hi> Pſal. 95. 3. And ſay with the Pſalmiſt: <hi>I will praiſe thee, for I am fearfully and wonderfully made; marvellous are thy works, and that my ſoul knoweth right well,</hi> Pſal. 139. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> You are ſtedfaſtly to believe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:150285:5"/> in God the Son; For that he is truly God the Apoſtle expreſly declares, <hi>Rom.</hi> 9. 5. where ſpeaking of Chriſt he ſaith, <hi>that he is over all God Bleſſed for ever;</hi> and ſo St. John, <hi>we are in him that is true, even in his Son Jeſus Chriſt, this is the true God, and Eternal life,</hi> 1 John. 5. 20. But we are not only to believe this Son to be God, but alſo that he redeem'd us, and all mankind. And that this Son of God paid the Price of Redemption for all Mankind, who can doubt that believes the Scripture? <hi>for there is one Mediator between God and man, the man Chriſt Jeſus, who gave himſelf a Ranſom for all,</hi> 1 Tim. 2. 5, 6. And again, <hi>he taſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Death for every man,</hi> Heb. 2. 9. And here common Gratitude prompts and directs you to your Duty. For <hi>ſince ye were bought with a Price, even with the Price of the moſt precious Blood of the Son of God, You are (ſtrongly oblig'd) to glorify God in your Bodies, and in your Spirits, which are his,</hi> 1 Cor. 6. 20.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> You are faithfully to believe in God the Holy Ghoſt, who ſanctifies you, and all the elect People of God,
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:150285:5"/> that the Holy Ghoſt is God, is plain from Acts the <hi>5th.</hi> verſes the 3<hi>d.</hi> and the <hi>4th.</hi> in the 3<hi>d.</hi> verſe St <hi>Peter</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pos'd this Queſtion, <hi>Why hath Satan filled thine heart to lie to the Holy Ghost?</hi> and becauſe <hi>Ananias</hi> thus lied to the Holy Ghoſt, he tells him verſe the <hi>4th. Thou haſt not lied unto Men, but unto God.</hi> Nay, before that, when the Pha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſees (upon our Saviours caſting out a Devil) aſcrib'd the operation to <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zebub</hi> the Prince of Devils: our Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our call'd this Sin, that Blaſphemy a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>which ſhall never be forgiven.</hi> By which words (the moſt Learned and Reverend Biſhop <hi>Pearſon</hi> obſerv'd, amongſt ſeveral other Arguments to that purpoſe, that) <hi>it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peareth, that there is a Sin or Blaſphemy againſt the Holy Ghoſt diſtinct from all other Sins and Blaſphemies committed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt God the Father, or the Son of God; that this Sin hath an Aggravation added unto it beyond other Sins and Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies: But if the Holy Spirit were no Perſon, the Sin could not be diſtinct from thoſe ſins which are committed againſt him whoſe ſpirit he is, and if he were a Perſon</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:150285:6"/> 
               <hi>created, the ſin could receive no ſuch Aggra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation beyond other Sins, and blaſphemies.</hi> and conſequently it remains that he is God.</p>
            <p>But we are not only to believe this Spirit to be God, but alſo that he is the Sanctifier of us, and of all the elect Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God. For what can be more po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitive and plain, than that the Sanctifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation of God's people is aſcrib'd to this Holy Spirit? for thus it runs in the words of the Apoſtle, <hi>Elect according to the foreknowledge of God the Father, through the ſanctification of the ſpirit,</hi> 1 Pet. 1. 2. And therefore from this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple of your Belief, you cannot but infer this to be your Duty, that ſince ye are <hi>a choſen Generation, a Royal Prieſt-hood, an Holy Nation, a peculiar People, you are oblig'd to ſhew forth his Praiſes, who hath call'd you out of darkneſs, into his marvelous light,</hi> 1 Pet. 2. 9.</p>
            <p>Thus then in the Divine Eſſence which is but one, there are three diſtinct Perſons <hi>viz.</hi> the Father, the Son, and the Holy Ghoſt, thus plainly diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed by their peculiar Properties. Nay, the Scripture does not only men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion theſe Properties, but alſo proceeds
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:150285:6"/> to the exact numbring of theſe Agents or Perſons in the Divine Eſſence, <hi>For there are three that bear Record in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghost, and theſe three are one,</hi> 1 John, 5. 7. and ſo again, <hi>Jeſus when he was baptized, went up ſtraightway out of the Water: and lo, the Heavens were o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd unto him, and he ſaw the ſpirit of God deſcending like a Dove, and light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing upon him. And lo, a voice from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, ſaying, This is my Beloved Son, in whom I am well pleaſed,</hi> Mat. 3. 16. 17. I mention no more Places to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe (tho' many occur) leſt I ſhould ſwell this little piece beyond its deſign<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed bounds: but that of St. Mathew. <hi>Chap.</hi> 28. 19. <hi>Go ye therefore, and teach all nations, Baptizing them in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> And yet notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding this Diſtinction of Agents, or Perſons there is but one entire Eſſence; for <hi>there is none other God but one,</hi> 1 Cor. 8. 4. <hi>and the Lord our God, is God only,</hi> Deut. 6. 4. And now, O young Man! ſince here is a main Principle of thy Profeſſion, here comes in a main Rule fot thy Practice. ſince there is a God,
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:150285:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:150285:7"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:150285:8"/> ſince there is but one God, therefore <hi>thou ſhalt Worſhip the Lord thy God, and him only ſhalt thou ſerve,</hi> Mat. 4. 10.</p>
            <p>But that the Father is God, the Son God, and the Holy Ghoſt God, and yet that there is but one God; how thus it is, and as to the manner how theſe things can be, this falls not within the Comprehenſion of thy Reaſon here on Earth; but hereafter in Heaven will (in all probability) be the ſubject of a moſt pleaſant and endleſs Enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainment. Thou mayſt with far more ſence, offer to contain all the Waters of the vaſt Ocean in the hollow of thine hand, than pretend to meaſure ſuch unfathomable and infinite Myſteries, by thy dark, and narrow, and ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Underſtanding. No, all that thou haſt to do in this caſe, is firmly to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve theſe, and all other Divine Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations and Principles of thy Holy Profeſſion, as the Reſurrection of the Dead, and eternal Life, and the like; and inſtead of prying too narrowly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to theſe unfathomable Depths, which the cleareſt and moſt enlarged Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of Mortals cannot bottom or find out, thou art to proceed to Pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice.
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:150285:8"/> For <hi>ſecret things belong to God, but reveal'd things to us and to our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,</hi> Deut. 29. 29. and if thou canſt not take meaſure of one of the Divine Attributes, nay, if to unfold the manner of thine own Exiſtence would puzzle thee, O never pretend here to diſcover the exact manner of the Being of a God! And yet; if upon the exerciſe of thy Senſe and Reaſon, thou believeſt the Exiſtence of the one <hi>viz.</hi> thine own Being: then upon the truth and goodneſs of God, and the exerciſe of thy Faith, believe the other; and ſo I paſs forward from <hi>Faith,</hi> directly to Practice, which is the Second thing I propos'd.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Then let me adviſe all Young Perſons, as a main Spur to all Goodneſs, as a ſtrong Safe-guard to all their Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, and as a powerful Antidote a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt, and reſtraint upon all Vices, to have an awful Regard, and conſtant Remembrance of the Divine Omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence and Omnipreſence, and the power of the Almighty. O conſider that <hi>God's eyes are over all your ways; and that his eye-lids try the children of men,</hi> Pſal. 11. 4. <hi>That he is about your Beds,</hi>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:150285:9"/> 
               <hi>and about your Paths, and ſpieth out all your ways. and that there is not a word in your tongue, nor a thought in your heart but he knoweth it altogether.</hi> Alas! 'tis in vain for thee to offer to draw the Curtain betwixt this all-ſeeing eye, and thy Deeds of Darkneſs: <hi>for the Darkneſs with God is no Darkneſs at all, but the night is as clear as the day, the Darkneſs and light are to him both alike,</hi> Pſ. 139. 12. All thy wanton and fooliſh Extravagancies and Rambles, all thy ſtiffneſs and ſtubbornneſs to all thy natural and political Parents, nay to thy ſpiritual Paſtors and Teachers, all thy head ſtrong and untam'd Paſſions in the full career of Luſt and Licenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſs, all thy forgetfulneſs of thy God and thy Duty in the days of thy Youth, all the ſtrong Biaſſes that thou art ready to clap upon thy Soul, bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee down to Senſuality and Sin, all thy jeſts upon Religion, and matters of the greateſt moment, and things of the moſt ſerious and an eternal Concern, all thy trifling with, and turning thy back upon the beſt of Friends, Friends that offer thee the moſt wholſom Counſel, and the ſafeſt Advice, Advice
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:150285:9"/> that (if follow'd) will preſerve thee from Danger and Evil, and counſel that (if obſerv'd) will enrich thee to all Eternity; all thy backwardneſs to do good, and all thy promptneſs and aptneſs to do evil, all the windings and foldings of thy heart, all thy fig-leav'd excuſes for thy paſt Iniquities, and all thy pretences for and palliations of thy preſent Tranſgreſſions; thy God plainly obſerves, he clearly beholds.</p>
            <p>Nay conſider, that as this all-ſearch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Eye beholds and obſerves all theſe things; ſo this all-powerful God is able to puniſh thee to the Uttermoſt, and none can ſtand before him when he is angry. He is able to conſume thee with the leaſt breath of his diſpleaſure, and to poſte thee away to Hell in the midſt of thy ſins, in the midſt of thy ſtrength, <hi>when</hi> (as Job ſpeaks) <hi>thy breaſts are full of milk,</hi> and <hi>thy bones are moiſtned with marrow,</hi> Job. 21. 24. And thou who canſt not now endure the leaſt of thy fingers to continue in a flame, <hi>how wilt thou then abide the conſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming Fire, how wilt thou be able to dwell with everlaſting burnings!</hi> Iſa. 33. 14.</p>
            <p>But then on the other hand thou
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:150285:10"/> who mindeſt thy Duty for thy encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement, conſider that this is the eye that neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps, but is continually intent upon all thy holy Works, all thy pure Words, all thy pi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous and chaſte Thoughts and Purpoſes: and this good God regiſters all thy good Deeds in the Book of his eternal Remembrance. And he is not unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous to forget, he is not unable to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence and repay thee for all thy labours, for all the Talents which thou haſt employ'd and husbanded to his Honour, and to thine own Advantage. As God ſees, and ſo will puniſh the wicked; ſo the Lord beholdeth the Righteous, and his Portion ſhall be with Plenty and Peace. And therefore, to reſtrain thee from Sin, and to puſh and ſpur thee on to Vertue and Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, <hi>O remember thy Creator,</hi> (this all-ſeeing and all-powerful God) <hi>in the days of thy Youth,</hi> Eccl. 12. 1.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Conſider, ye Young Perſons, the Boundleſs Love of your moſt Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious God towards you. He rais'd you up into Creatures of a ſublime and noble Being, whereras he might have made you mere Stocks and Stones, or
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:150285:10"/> Creatures more deform'd and ghaſtly than they. He paid a Ranſom for you of ineſtimable value, even the Blood of his only begotten Son, a Gift as great as Heaven could beſtow, or man receive. Nay your Lot (to whom I write) is fal'n in a wealthy Place, and you have a goodly Heritage, it is the kindneſs of good Fortune, nay of a good Providence, and of tender Compaſſion, that you are born of Chriſtian Parents, that you are receiv'd into the Boſom of the Church, that you are enter'd into Covenant with God, and have vow'd Obedience to him, and have put your ſelves under his Divine Protection, and the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of his Grace. Nay more, you are now grown ſtrong, and fit for Gods ſervice, and the Diſcharge of Duties. And now ſhall he that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on you Life, He that hath ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſom'd you from eternal ſlavery with the Sacrifice of his only Son, He that gives you Temporal and ſpiritual health and ſtrength; ſhall he have no Return for theſe many, theſe endear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Uouchſafements? Certainly you are of better Diſpoſitions than to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quite
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:150285:11"/> ſo good a God ſo fooliſhly, ſo unworthily, ſo Ungratefully. Cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly you would not deal thus with your natural Parents, with your fellow Brethren, with your hired Servants, and much leſs ſurely with your God, Who gives you life, and breath, and all things, the mercies of the right hand, and of the left, the Bleſſings of this preſent life, and the Overtures of another, and a far better. O often reflect and meditate upon the Love of God! and then if there be the leaſt ſpark of Grace, of good nature in you, it muſt needs draw you on to ſerve the Lord, and to keep his commandments.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Let me perſwade Young Perſons to live in a cheerful Obedience to them that are ſet over them. Now thoſe that are ſet over them are their Temporal, or their Spiritual Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours. Their Temporal Governours are the King and thoſe commiſſioned by him, or their natural Parents, or Maſters. And O how inviting and endearing, how pleaſing and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy is an humble, and Obedient deportment to each of theſe! Nay 'tis not only endearing and praiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:150285:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> but alſo attended with the Bleſſing of God, and crownd with temporal comforts. And as they who make little or nothing, of the Breach of this great Duty many times ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denly periſh, and come to a fearful end: ſo, (that, the God of Order may ſignalize his Divine Providence in the World) thoſe that hono'r their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Mother, their days are often prolong'd here: or if ſometimes they fall ſhort of <hi>that,</hi> they are lengthned out in an eternal Canaan, in the City of God, in the Land that the Lord gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth them. Nay tis a common Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervation, that as ſtubborn and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumacious children often come to be whipt in their own Rod, and to read their ſin by their puniſhment, by ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving children of their own as ſtubborn and ſtiffnecked, as they were to their Parents: So obedient children have a full Recompence return'd into their Boſom, by having afterwards children as obſervant of, and as Dutiful to them, as they were formerly obedient to their Parents. Or if herein they fall ſhort, God makes up the want in ſome more ſignal, and ſupereminent Grace, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:150285:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> Favo'r. As ever therefore you hope to gain the good Opinion of men, the Grace and Favo'r of God, and to have Obedient children and ſubmiſſive Servants ſhew your ſelves ſubmiſſive, and obedient to your Temporal Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours. <hi>Honour thy Father and Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, which is the Firſt Commandment with Promiſe,</hi> Eph. 6. 2.</p>
            <p>But beſides theſe Temporal Parents, there are your ſpiritual Paſtors and Teachers; and let me perſwade you young Perſons to carry it to theſe with a due Reſpect, and eſteem. The ſame God who is the God of Order hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed theſe to watch for your ſouls, Nay theſe are <hi>the Ambaſſadors of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 5. 29. But tho' they are thus appointed, tho' they plainly prove their Commiſſion from Chriſt, tho' they preach nothing but ſound words and the Will of God, nay more, tho' they labour in the Word and Doctrine: yet if thou deſpiſe their Labours, and take up low Opinions of their Abilities and Endowments; you then fruſtrate all their Pains and Patience as to your ſelves; and their Prayers, (as to you) and exhortations, and the word prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched will be of none Effect; <hi>not being</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:150285:12"/> 
               <hi>mixed with Faith, (and eſteem) in them that hear it.</hi> Thoſe miniſters there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that are choſen by God, that are ſelected and ſet apart by the Paſtors of the Church, that are eſtabliſht by the Laws of the Land and ſet over you; as long as you may obtain the means of ſalvation under them, as long as they preach nothing contrary to a holy Faith, and good manners, and as long as ther's nothing ſinful in their communion; O keep ye ſtedfaſtly to them, and encourage their Labours by your conſtant communion with them! and by this means, you'l highly contribute to the preſerving of Peace in the Church, in the ſtate, in your Neighbourhood, and in your private Families. I conclude this head with the words of the Bleſſed Apoſtle, 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 5. 12, 13.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>I beſeech you Brethren</hi> (even you young men as Brethren) <hi>to know them (i. e.</hi> to own and acknowledge them with reſpect) <hi>which labour among you, and are over you in the Lord, and admoniſh you: and to eſteem them very highly in love for their works ſake, and be at Peace among your ſelves.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="18" facs="tcp:150285:13"/>
            <p> 
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Let me adviſe young Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons to weigh and conſider things, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they are too intent upon them, and too eager in the purſuit of them. Youth indeed is the peculiar Age, and ſcene of <hi>much</hi> haſte and Precipitancy: and conſequently of Wiſdom and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence <hi>not over much.</hi> How many Young Perſons have done that by one overhaſty Act: Which they have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pented of afterwards, all the days of their Life? How many have done that with more haſte than good ſpeed; Which they could not but repent of all the days of their Life? How many by a wild Debauch have broken their healthful, and ſtrong Bodies in pieces, and ever after carried crazy conſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions along with them even to the Grave? How many upon a Venturous Reſolve have thrown away upon the turn of a Die the largeſt Demeſnes; and ever afterward either ſhabb'd upon their Relations and Neighbours, or elſe have taken deſperate Courſes, or down right Beggery for their Ordinary Companion, and common courſe of Life? How many by a ſudden fit of Anger have broacht their Brothers
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:150285:13"/> blood, and thereby ſo blotted and blur'd their own Eſcutcheon, that all the Waters of Repentance afterwards could never waſh out the ſtains? Nay how many out of an eager thirſt of Revenge, have found themſelv's moſt miſerably diſappointed: and inſtead of ridding the world of their Adverſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, have ſent away their own ſouls at the point of their enemies ſpear? theſe and the like are the raſh attempts of youth: and theſe and the like Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequences are the fruits of their Folly. O let me adviſe you then, before you put your ſelv's upon theſe, or the like deſperate Attempts, ſeriouſly to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider what the end of theſe things will be. O weigh your Pleaſures and your Pains in an equal Ballance, and for a minute of miſtaken joy, never truck away an Eternity of ſolid ſatisfaction! O never ſhew your ſelves ſo fooliſh, as for once gratifying of your Bodies, of your paſſion: to ruin and damn both ſoul and body for ever! O ſhew your ſelves to be perſons of more ſence and Reaſon, and where there is the deepeſt and moſt laſting ſorrow ſhun it; where there is the moſt perfect
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:150285:14"/> and long-liv'd Pleaſure purſue it; and take the Advice of the excellent Son of Syrac: Eccleſiaſticus the <hi>7<hi rend="sup">th.</hi>
               </hi> 36. Whatſoever thou takeſt in hand re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member the end, and thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver do amiſs.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fifthly,</hi> Let me perſwade Young men to mind, and to be diligent in their reſpective Vocations and callings, this is the very Age that is moſt pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per for labour, and is peculiarly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>apted for Buſineſs. Children indeed have neither ſtrength nor Under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding for the diſpatch of Buſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs: and old Age is commonly at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended with <hi>that</hi> feebleneſs, and thoſe Infirmities which are inconſiſtent with heavy Burdens, and hard Toyl. No, 'tis you, (who have vigorous ſpirits, and ſtrong ſinews) that are to bear the burden, and heat of the Day. And for you then <hi>to fold up your hands with the Sluggard, and to cry out a little more ſleep, a little more ſlumber,</hi> Prov. 6. 10. when the Task is required of you in the midſt of your ſpring: What is this but to defame, and to darken your Glory; by ſhewing your ſelv's to be lazy ſots, and drowſy Drones?
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:150285:14"/> Nay let me tell you, that in this Age, your ſpirits are ſo brisk and active, that you cannot but be intent upon ſome Action or other: Either buſy you muſt be, with thoſe things that are Vertuous and good: or elſe your minds will be bent upon thoſe things that are baſe and Vicious. Nay he that in this Age ſtands in the mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket Place all the day idle: he expo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes himſelf as a chapman to Satan. And whereas <hi>the Devil goes about the Earth to and fro' ſeeking whom he (may intangle and allure,) devour and destroy,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 8. This ſilly Soul is taken Captive by him at his Will, and does the Devils Work to his hands, and falls a Victim to him, without the pains of a purchaſe. 'Tis ſad to conſider (but a moſt certain as well as a much to be lamented truth) that Idleneſs is the very Mother and Nurſe of much Evil. And that when we have nothing to do, I mean when we will have nothing to do: Then the Guards of our Souls are taken off, and then the Young Man lies open to all the Inſtigations of Satan, and to all the Allurements of all the Devils
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:150285:15"/> Factors and Agents. And then we are eaſily drawn in to Company keep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and from that, we are wheedled to Drunkenneſs and Debauchery, and ſo forward, to gameing and Lewdneſs: and often, too often to thoſe Courſes, which bring a Man to Temporal Death too ſoon, as well as to eternal. O if theſe things are dreadful to be the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment of your Thoughts: See that ye kill the Cockatrice in the ſhell, and ſhun the Cauſe and occaſion, that ſo ye may more eaſily avoid the diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mal conſequence and Effect! <hi>And be not ſlothful in Buſineſs,</hi> Rom, 12. 11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Sixthly,</hi> Let me beſeech Young Perſons not to buſy their Fancies a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout Modes and Faſhions: but to apparel themſelves in modeſt attire. I well know that 'tis eaſy and common to reply in this Caſe, that Pride is lodg'd in the heart: and ſo is not to be learnt or known from the outward habit. And that ſome Beggers are as proud of their ſhreds and rags, as other Perſons of Worth and Honour are of their diſtinguiſhing Garments, and their gorgeous attire. I grant indeed, that as there are Diſtinctions of men;
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:150285:15"/> ſo there ſhould be Diſtinctions of Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parel: and that ſuch a Garb which would be too fine and ſplendid for one; would be a ſuit too ſorbid and mean for another. I grant alſo that as Diſtinction of ſexes ought to be ſhewed by Garments, ſo alſo different Ranks, and peculiar Perſons and Officers are to be known by diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhing habits, Since theſe things are agreeable to the Laws of that Great God who is the God of Order. Nay I grant ſtill further, that Pride lies in the heart, and not in the outward habit, and that one man may carry an humble and lowly Soul in a rich Dreſs, Whereas another may have a lofty and exalted Spirit even in a borrow'd, or unpaid-for Garment. But ſtill let me advice thee who aboundeſt with theſe expreſſions, and Excuſes for thy gay clothing; to have a great Jealouſy, and a ſtrict watch over thy heart and ways. Thy Saviour tels thee, <hi>that the Tree is known by its Fruits,</hi> Luke, 6. 44. And our Deſires and Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons are diſcover'd and remarkt by our words and Actions. And there's ſcarce any plainer Indication of the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:150285:16"/> Levity (I had almoſt ſaid of the Wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tonneſs) of our Minds; than by the Levity and Gaudineſs of our Garbs. Away then with thoſe Excuſes that thou mayeſt be lowly, and that thou art humble at thy heart and Soul when at the ſame time thou deckeſt thy Body with a Garb which is not ſuitable for, but Vaſtly beyond thy Birth and Ranke. Nay how wilt thou anſwer it to thy great Creator who made thee thus and thus? Whereas thou offereſt to diſguiſe, to correct his Workman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip; and in effect ſayeſt unto him, Why haſt thou made me thus? How canſt thou imagine that he will own thee for his Creature? When thou offereſt to Mould thy ſelf as it were into another Figure by thy ſtrange Guiſes, which neither tend to the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerving of health, nor to the differen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing of Sex, nor the diſtinguiſhing of Order. O ſhew thy Humility of mind by thy works and decent Apparel! and inſtead of theſe florid Faſhions Which one Flower in thy Garden, one ſingle Tulip far out-ſhines: <hi>be clothed with Humility,</hi> 1 Pet. 5. 5. <hi>and put on the Ornament of a meek and quiet</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:150285:16"/> 
               <hi>Spirit, Which is in the ſight of God of great Price.</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 4. And ſince Garments were given as a covering of Nakedneſs, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3. 21. O Never make thy ſhame thy Glory, and be not Proud of thy loſs and want of Innocence and Perfection!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Seventhly,</hi> Let me perſwade Young Perſons carefully to avoid evil Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany: And to joyn themſelv's to the Society of ſuch as Serve God. As ever they value their Reputations, as ever they tender the Welfare of their Souls and Bodies, as ever they mean to ſecure their ſafety, as ever they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign to promote their temporal and their Eternal Intereſt: this is a Duty which is principally to be regarded. Evil Company is the very Bane and Ruſt of Religion and good morals. And all the ſeeds of Vertue which Chriſtian Parents have moſt carefully ſown, (tho having taken Root, and grown up into a Strong blade, yet) they have often been ſoon blaſted and conſum'd, by a ſwarm of theſe worſe than Egyptian Locuſts. O what but wicked Company hath made Young Perſons who have afforded the moſt
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:150285:17"/> promiſing hopes of an enriching Crop and harveſt, moſt fatally to miſcarry: and to become twice the Children of Hell more than they that inveigled them! O let the ſad Misfortunes, and lamentable Ruin's of ſuch, make thee to ſhun their ſteps, ſince the end of thoſe ways is Death! And tho' their Converſation be never ſo accompliſht, Witty, and inviting: yet ſhun their fellowſhip as much as thou Wouldeſt avoid his, who tho' he may be ſmooth and ſeems endearing, yet hath the ſpots of an infectious Plague upon him. And that thou mayeſt do this effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, joyn thy ſelf to, and enter into cloſe fellowſhip with them that love, and ſerve God: Where thou mayeſt be Religious at an eaſy Rate, and gain not only plain precepts, but alſo in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viting Patterns to goodneſs, which will ſilently ſlide into thy Soul, and almoſt inſenſibly draw and carry thee on, and convey thee into the Land of the Living. Theſe will whet thy Deſires, and ſharpen thy Appetites, and enflame thy longings after God and Goodneſs, and ſtrengthen thy Reſolutions, and abett and improve
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:150285:17"/> thy Chriſtian Courage, and ſhew thee how to be an hardy Souldier of Chriſt Jeſus, and make thee more than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querour through Chriſt that loves thee. O keep that Company that ſhall be inſtilling ſome good Leſſon, ſome ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Advice into thee, and that ſhall preſcribe a good Example: But ſhun that Society that infuſes Poiſon into thy very Vitals, and corrupts thy pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious Soul by their Words and Works, by their ill Counſels and worſe Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſations. And always remember the Words which the Apoſtle recites, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 33. <hi>Evil Communications corrupt good Manners.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, Let me perſwade Young Perſons to be Courteous and Obliging, in each Relation wherein they ſtand. Are your Fortunes fair, and your Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes large, ſhew your ſelves to be ſuch as are Free born: by ſuch a carriage as may loudly proclaim your Birth and Education. Or are your Eſtates con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fin'd in a narrow Compaſs: you have much leſs Reaſon to boaſt, and to bear high, to diſoblige and to provoke: ſince you know not how ſoon Poverty may ſteal in upon you and how ſoon
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:150285:18"/> you may ſtand in need of the help, of the Relief of thoſe very Neighbours whom you now deſpiſe. Nay you own your ſelves to be Chriſtians, and therefore learn of the Holy Jeſus to be meek and lowly, <hi>Who, when he was reviled, reviled not again, when he ſuff<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er'd, he threatened not, but committed himſelf to him who judgeth righteouſly,</hi> Heb. 12. 3. He was ſo ſuffering, and ſo kind in his ſufferings, that he died for his Enemies that they might live for ever. And for thoſe enemies which put him to Death he thus prayed, <hi>Father forgive them for they know not what they do,</hi> Luke, 23. 24.</p>
            <p>And now canſt thou read, canſt thou hear this Paſſage with any Roughneſs, or Impatience upon thy Spirit? with any Anger or Indignation againſt thoſe who affront, or ſcourge thee? O ſince the Holy Jeſus my Innocent Saviour thus ſuffer'd (mayſt thou ſay) who never did, nor ſpake, nor thought any thing amiſs, Well may I juſtly ſmart, who act, or ſpeak or deſign few things well. And ſince he bare his Burden patiently, and pray'd even for his Perſecutors, for his murderers:
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:150285:18"/> 
               <hi>O</hi> 'tis much more my bounden Duty to forgive, as I have great, and often need to be forgiven my ſelf; and to be obliging, <hi>pitiful, and Courteous,</hi> 1 Pet. 3. 8.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> Let it be your daily Buſineſs as it is your Duty, to pray earneſtly to God, to work in you both to Will and to do according to his good Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure. Never think that either you or your Teachers are able to give you Grace, or to ſecure your Vertues: without the helping Hand of Heaven, that giveth to all liberally that ask him: Or without that Watchful Eye that neither ſlumbers nor ſleeps. No, <hi>every good and Perfect Gift cometh down from above,</hi> James, 1. 17.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And Paul may Plant, and Apollos may Water: But ſtill it muſt be God that gives the encreaſe,</hi> 1 Cor. 3. 6. And therefore that the hand of God may hold you up, that his watchful Lye may be over you, that he may Guide you into the ways of Truth and Peace, and that he may Strengthen, Stabliſh, Settle you, it is your Intereſt no leſs than your Duty, to beg his Grace. Nay it is your Honour, no
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:150285:19"/> leſs than your Intereſt and Duty, thus to repair to your God. For you who are duſt and Aſhes to ſpeak unto the Lord, for you, who are worthleſs Beings to have free Recourſe to a Principle of abſolute Perfection, for you, who are notorious Sinners to draw nigh unto the Holy Lord God of Hoſts, for you, who are the mean<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt of Subjects to unboſom your ſelves to, and to beg Boons and Favor's of the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords: this is ſo great a Priviledge and Hon'or, that (methinks) it needs no further Motive to enforce it. Only let me re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mind you, that the manifold, and great Temptations which your Age expoſes, and too often inclines you to may juſtly make you to cry mightily unto your God, and often; and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly to beg ſaying; <hi>Save Lord or <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap> periſh,</hi> Mat. 8. 25. Often pray for the Pardon of your Sins paſt, and for the Supplies of Gods Grace for the time to come.</p>
            <p>And now in a Word, that I may not omit recommending any important Duty which appertains to you, Often conſider, and duly weigh thoſe ſhort,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:150285:19"/> but moſt comprehenſive leſſons drawn up for you in your Church Catechiſm: which I deſire you frequently to peruſe, and faithfully to remember; now there you thus read. My Duty toward God, is to believe in him, to fear him, and to love him with all my heart, with all my Mind, with all my Soul, and with all my ſtrength: to Worſhip him, to give him thanks to put my whole truſt in him, to call upon him, to hono'r his Holy Name and his Word and to ſerve him truly all the days of my Life.</p>
            <p>And my Duty towards my Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour is to love him as my ſelf, and to do to all men as I would they ſhould do unto me. To love, honour and ſuccour my Father and Mother. To Honour and obey the King, and all that are put in Authority under him. To ſubmit my ſelf to all my Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours, Teachers, Spiritual Paſtors and Maſters. To order my ſelf lowly and reverently to all my betters. To hurt no Body by Word or Deed. To be true and juſt in all my Dealings. To bear no Malice nor Hatred in my heart. To keep my Hands from picking and
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:150285:20"/> Stealing, and my Tongue from Evil-Speaking, Lying and Slandering. To keep my Body in Temperance, Sober<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and Chaſtity. Not to covet no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> deſire other mens Goods; But to Learn and Labour truly to get min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> own living, and to do my Duty in that State of Life unto which it ſhall pleaſe God to call me.</p>
            <p>And now I paſs on directly to the laſt thing which I propos'd, and that is: to lay before you a few General conſiderations, on purpoſe further to promote the Practice of that <hi>Advice which I have already given.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt, Conſider how eaſy tis for you, in compariſon of ſome others, to be Religious and good. Whilſt you are untainted, whilſt the Powers and Faculties of your Souls are Vigorous and Lively, whilſt you have not ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſtomed your ſelves to any evil way, whilſt you are ſtrangers to the faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onable ſins of the Age, whilſt you have not run with others to the ſame exceſs of Riot, whilſt the Helliſh Language of Oaths and Curſes is terrible to you<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and all manner of profaneneſs appears to you in a Monſtrous and ghaſtly
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:150285:20"/> Shape: it muſt needs be eaſie to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrain you from what you dread and abhor. Nay if you have ſometimes fallen, and receiv'd ſome few bruiſes, yet how far more eaſily may you re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover your ſelves than thoſe who for many years have lain wallowing in their filthineſs? Moreover, to your great encouragement conſider, that now your Souls are active, and your limbs ſtrong, to run with patience <hi>the Holy Race that is ſet before you:</hi> and you may well <hi>fight</hi> with the greateſt Aſſurance <hi>the good fight of Faith: Now ye are ſtrong, and may eaſily overcome the wicked one,</hi> 1 John 2. 14.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To move you the more, conſider how acceptable your early Piety will be, to that God which ye Worſhip. Your remembring your Creator in the days of your youth, and your firſt fruits will be a Sacrifice wherewith God will be well pleaſed. Whereas the Oblation only of dry bones, and decayed ſinews, eſpecially ſuch bones as have been drain'd by ſin, ſuch ſinews as have been enfeebl'd by Iniquity, will be only an abomina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion unto the Lord. <hi>If ye offer the blind</hi>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:150285:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
               <hi>for Sacrifice is it not evil? and if ye offer it now unto thy Governour: will he be pleaſed with thee, or accept thy Perſon ſaith the Lord of Hoſts?</hi> Malac. 1. 8. Now if a Temporal Prince will reject ſuch a preſent with a moſt fiery Indignation: With what confidence then can we lay ſuch a Sacrifice upon the Altar of the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords?</p>
            <p>But this is not your Caſe at preſent ye Young men: and God Grant that hereafter (when old) it may never be your Fate. Now you need not to doubt, but that if you offer up the ſtrength and Beauty of Holineſs, it will be accepted. If now with the wiſe Virgins you get oyl, and trim your Lamps: you will ere long be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived into the Bride-Grooms Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> Pleaſe to conſider how much your remaining life depends upon your preſent Religious Efforts: and how gradually you'l go on, when you are once well begun. How eaſily will you damp and diſpirit all the enemies to your ſalvation, and under what Diſcomfiture and deſpair will you ſend them away, when you baffle and rout
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:150285:21"/> them in the firſt Aſſaults that they make upon you? Nay how much may your early and firm Reſolutions tend to the reclaiming of this degenerate Age, or at leaſt to the reforming of the next Generation? If the skill and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duct of one man made way for his Son to conquer all the parts of the world which he became acquainted with: how far then may your united Forces extend to the pulling down of the ſtrong holds of Satan, and the ſubduing of the powers of darkneſs: to the vanquiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Sin, and to the raiſing and eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhing of the Throne of Vertue? O conſider how far you may ſpread theſe Spiritual Victories and Triumphs, and may make your Companions and thoſe that come after you, more than Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querors!</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> pleaſe to conſider, that you (notwithſtanding all your health and ſtrength) may ſoon be called away to another ſtage, either of endleſs weal or woe. Go and take the Dimenſions of the Graves in your Church Yards, and youl find many of a ſhorter ſize than your ſelves. And I am ſure that you had not, nay that you have not a
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:150285:22"/> more certain Leaſe of your lives, than they had. O therefore make no long tarrying to turn unto the Lord your God, and put it not of from day to day; leſt your Fate, leſt your God come ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dainly, and ſnatch you away and there be none to deliver you. Conſider that Time and Opportunity will ſoon be no more. And therefore inſtantly make it your buſineſs to ſpend your days to good purpoſe, in reading the Word of God, in pious and profitable medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, in reflecting upon and renew<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Baptiſmal Covenant, and in frequent receiving the Holy Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion. And above all, labour to be true, and juſt, and good at your very hearts and Souls; and induſtrious, and Uſeful, and benificial in your Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration. And ſtrive earneſtly to fit and qualify your ſelves for an Eternity of the pureſt Pleaſures: that ſo you may reliſh the joys of Heaven whenever you ſhall be receiv'd into thoſe everlaſting manſions, and may delightfully feaſt upon that fulneſs of joy which is in the preſence of God, and with continual deſire drink of thoſe Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers of Pleaſure which flow at his
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:150285:22"/> right hand for evermore. <hi>And may be meet to be partakers of the Inheritance of the Saints in light,</hi> Col. 1. 12. And in the proſpect of theſe enriching po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſſeſſions, of theſe never fading Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures break off all delays, throw aſide all hindrances and excuſes, and ſay not, I will begin to be good, when I begin to ſtoop towards the Grave, and when old age tells me that I muſt ſoon leave this World, then will I prepare for the next; and when I feel this earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle to tremble and ready to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve, and to be taken in pieces: then will I ſeek out for another Fabric, an houſe not made with hands, eternal in the Heavens. But inſtead of theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>certain, frivolous, and fooliſh Delays: to day if you will hear Gods voice harden not your hearts. And remember that the wiſeſt Man in the World is not able to foretel what one day may bring forth. <hi>Ye know not what ſhall be on the morrow. For what is your life? It is even as a Vapour that appeareth for a little time, and then vaniſheth away,</hi> James 4. 14.</p>
            <p>Since then the day of your departure is ſo uncertain, be ye always ready:
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:150285:23"/> that ſo when the King of Terrors ſhall ſeize you, he may not with aſtoniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment ſurprize you; but that Death (being diſarm'd of its ſting) may ſerve to compoſe you for the Sweeteſt ſleep, and ſo you may lay you down in Peace and take your reſt. O watch continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, for <hi>ye know not at what hour your Lord will come,</hi> Mat. 24. 42.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Laſtly,</hi> For a full inducement to the Practice of theſe Precepts, and for the Obſervation of whatever is good: often remember, that the more Religious you now are, and the more that you influ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence others to be Religious here: the more you ſhall be rewarded here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after. Know and be aſſur'd that if you carefully husband, and induſtriouſly (by Gods Bleſſing) improve your ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lents, you ſhall receive a proportion<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able Recompence of Reward from your Gracious Lord and Maſter, Mat. 25. 21. And let the words of the prophet Daniel continually dwell with you, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12. 3. <hi>They that be wiſe ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the Firma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: and they that turn many unto Righteouſneſs as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="39" facs="tcp:150285:23"/>
            <p> Theſe things out of pure tenderneſs to your immortal Souls O ye young Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons! I recommend to you. And now God of his infinite Goodneſs give you Grace to obſerve them, that ſo ye may reap the Rewards of your Religion, and be happy for ever.</p>
            <p>To God the Father, God the Son, and God the Holy Ghoſt be all Honour and Glory, both now and evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="prayers">
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:150285:24"/>
               <head>PRAYERS.</head>
               <p>ALmighty and Everlaſting God, who hateſt nothing that thou haſt made, and doſt forgive the Sins of all them that are penitent, create and make in me a new and contrite Heart, that I wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily lamenting my ſins, and acknowledging my wretchedneſs, may obtain of thee the God of all mercy, perfect Remiſſion and forgiveneſs, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord Amen.</p>
               <p>ALmighty and Everlaſting God give unto me the Increaſe of Faith, Hope, and Charity; and that I may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain that which thou doſt promiſe, make me to love that which thou doſt command, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord Amen.</p>
               <p>O God who haſt prepar'd for them that love thee, ſuch good things as paſs mans <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding; pour into mine heart ſuch love towards thee, That I loving thee above all things, may obtain thy Promiſes, which exceed all that we can deſire, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord Amen.</p>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:150285:24"/>
               <p> ALmighty God, who ſeeſt that we have no power of our ſelves to help our ſelves; keep me both outwardly in my Body and inwardly in my Soul: that I may be defended from all Adverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties which may happen to the Body, and from all evil thoughts which may aſſault and hurt the Soul, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord Amen.</p>
               <p>O God the Creator and Preſerver of all mankind, I humbly beſeech thee for all ſorts and conditions of men, that thou wouldeſt be pleaſed to make thy ways known unto them, thy ſaving health unto all nations; more eſpecially I pray for the good Eſtate of the Catholick Cburch, that it may be ſo guided and Governed by thy good Spirit, that all who profeſs and call themſelves Chriſtians, may be led into the way of truth, and hold the Faith in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of Spirit, in the Bond of Peace, and in Righteouſneſs of life, finally I commend to thy Fatherly goodneſs all thoſe who are any way afflicted, or diſtreſſed in Mind, Body or Eſtate; that it may pleaſe thee to comfort and relieve them according to their ſeveral neceſſities, giving them Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:150285:25"/> under their ſufferings, and a happy iſſue out of all their Afflictions. And this I beg for Jeſus Chriſt his ſake Amen.</p>
               <p>ALmighty God Father of all mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, I thine unworthy Servant do give thee moſt humble and hearty thanks, for all thy goodneſs and loving kindneſs to me, and to all men. I bleſs thee for my Creation, Preſervation, and all the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of this Life. But above all for thine ineſtimable love in the Redemption of the World by our Lord Jeſus Chriſt; for the means of Grace, and for the hope of Glory. And I beſeech thee give me that due ſence of all thy mercies, that mine heart may be unfeignedly thankful, and that I may ſhew forth thy Praiſe, not only with my lips, but in my life, by giving up my ſelf to thy ſervice, and by walking before thee in Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lineſs and Righteouſneſs all my days, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord; to whom with thee and the Holy Ghost be all Honour and Glory, world without end. Amen.</p>
               <p>LOrd of all power and might, who art the Author and giver of all good things: graft in my heart the Love of
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:150285:25"/> thy Name, increaſe in me true Religion, nouriſh me with all Goodneſs, and of thy great mercy keep me in the ſame, through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord. Amen.</p>
               <p>GRant O Lord, that as I am baptized into the Death of thy Bleſſed Son our Saviour Jeſus Chriſt; ſo by continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al mortifying my corrupt Affections, I may be buried with him, and that through the Grave and Gate of Death, I may paſs to my joyful Reſurrection, for his merits who died and was buried, and roſe again for us, thy Son Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, Amen.</p>
               <p>PRevent me O Lord, in all my doings, with thy moſt Gracious Favour, and further me with thy continual help, that in all my Works begun, continued, and ended in thee, I may glorify thy Holy Name and finally by thy mercy may obtain everlaſting Life through Jeſus Chriſt our Lord, in whoſe Name and words I call upon thee further, ſaying Our Father which art in, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:150285:26"/>
               <p> 
                  <hi>The Grace of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and the Love of God, and the Fellowſhip of the Holy Ghoſt, be with me now, and evermore</hi> Amen.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="errata">
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>IN page 10. l: 24 for thou, read you; p 23. l 20. for advice, r. adviſe; p 34 l. 1. after <hi>offer,</hi> r. <hi>the lame and ſick, is it not evil? offer it</hi> p. 36. l. 19. for benificial, r. beneficial.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
